"Do Low Level Laser Therapy Devices
Work for Hair Loss?"
In my book, How Not to Age,
I discuss all the drugs,
foods, supplements,
and surgeries that can treat
age-related hair loss,
but what about non-dietary,
non-drug,
non-surgical interventions?
Autologous platelet-rich plasma,
where concentrated portions
of your own blood
is repeatedly injected
into your scalp,
appears to have an efficacy
similar to the available drugs,
though the available evidence
is considered insufficient
to recommend it,
and so remains unapproved
in the U.S. or Europe
for hair restoration purposes.
Scalp Botox
is also not recommended.
The thought was
that relaxing scalp muscles
might improve blood flow,
but when actually put
to the test
actually caused hair loss
in some pilot study
participants.
Then, there are lasers.
In the 1960s,
a Hungarian physician
published the paper,
"The effect of laser beams
on the growth of hair in mice,"
detailing
a serendipitous discovery
that a low-powered ruby laser
increased the hair growth
on the shaved backs of mice.
The mechanism appears to be
increased blood flow.
The floodgates opened
when the FDA cleared
the first low-level
laser therapy device
for age-related
pattern hair loss in 2007,
and now, there are clinics
advertising lasers
for everything
from tennis elbow
to "scrotal rejuvenation."
There have been at least ten
randomized, controlled trials
of low-level
laser therapy devices
for hair loss, and the efficacy
has been found comparable
or even superior to the drugs.
They are noninvasive and appear
to be relatively safe.
Mild side effects
include itching, acne,
and scalp tenderness
that usually resolves
within two weeks.
Reviews typically conclude
that laser therapy
may be a promising alternative
to drugs and scalpels,
but there remains
considerable skepticism
within the dermatology community
and for good reason.
Most of the laser therapy trials
were funded
by the manufacturers
of the tested products
themselves.
This is true of hair loss
treatments across the board,
but laser studies appear
particularly reticent
to provide visual evidence
or inquire
about perhaps the most important
outcome of all,
patient satisfaction.
When the first independent study
was performed,
blinded evaluations
of before-and-after photographs
could not detect a difference
in hair density or caliber.
In two studies that compared
subjective satisfaction
between laser
and sham placebo devices,
no significant difference
could be found either.
In other words,
from the patient's perspective,
they just plain don't work.
So, while there are
statistically significant
improvements
in hair density and thickness,
there may be little clinically
significant improvement.
If you want to give them
a try anyway,
there are at least 29
FDA-cleared devices
currently on the market.
There have been no head-to-head
studies between them,
but based on measured outcomes,
there appear to be
no difference
between the comb-style
and hat-style devices,
though those containing
laser diodes exclusively
may have an edge over devices
that include a mix
of both laser diodes and LED.
Do not look into the light,
as prolonged retinal exposure
could be damaging.
Thankfully,
at least most cap designs
have a built-in safety shut-off
to avoid accidental
eye exposure.
Otherwise,
besides general safety caveats
about using
electrical contraptions
in or around water,
such devices are
considered safe,
though they are contraindicated
for those with cancer
of the scalp
due to the potential
for stimulatory effects.